{"tossups": [{"question": "While serving on the D.C. Circuit, this future Supreme Court justice ruled in favor of the Bush administration\u2019s military tribunals in<em> Hamdan v.</em> <em>Rumsfeld</em>. This man denounced the \u201cindividual mandate\u201d as excessive under the Commerce Clause, but defended it under Congress\u2019s authority as a tax in the majority opinion to<em> NFIB v. Sebelius</em>. This man gained his current post in 2005 after the death of his predecessor, William Rehnquist. The Affordable Care Act was upheld by a mostly-conservative Supreme Court led by, for the point, what current Chief Justice?", "answer": "John G.<b> Roberts</b> Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Haim Moussa Douek was the last leader of these people in Egypt, having left in 1972. The Ethiopian-based Falashas are \u201cwandering\u201d groups of these people, some of whom were rescued during Operation Solomon. The Lemba people claim common ancestry with these people, though their matrilineal descent is disputed. Some of these people were repatriated from Sudanese refugee camps under the Law of Return. For the point, name these people who likely migrated to Africa from present-day Israel.", "answer": "<b> Jew</b>ish people", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "An 1861 riot on this city\u2019s Pratt Street led to the first deaths of the U.S. Civil War. George Peabody, the father of modern philanthropy, was based in this city, where he established his namesake Institute and Library. A railroad named for this city and Ohio led to prosperity for this city during the 1830s, which is home to Johns Hopkins University. For the point, name this city named for the Catholic founder of its home state of Maryland.", "answer": "<b> Baltimore</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In one speech, this man praised Jacob Ruppert, Ed Barrow, Joe McCarthy, and others, and said that despite his \u201cbad break,\u201d this successor of Wally Pipp considered himself \u201cthe luckiest man on the face of this earth.\u201d This man\u2019s most famous accomplishment was bested in 1995 by \u201cIron Man\u201d Cal Ripken when he played in his 2,131st consecutive game. For the point, name this New York Yankees first baseman who died in 1941 from ALS, a disease that now bears his name.", "answer": "Henry Louis \u201cLou\u201d<b> Gehrig</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "The Seguro Obrero Massacre took place in this country in response to an attempted 1938 National Socialist coup. Carlos Ib\u00b4a\u02dcnez del Campo began the nationalization of this country\u2019s largest industry; that process was completed by a Popular Unity-backed president who defeated Jorge Alessandri in 1970. That leader of this country was overthrown in a 1973 coup by a dictator advised in economics by the Chicago Boys. For the point, name this nation led by Augusto Pinochet after the overthrow of Salvador Allende.", "answer": "<b> Chile</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This ruler survived an assassination attempt in which his winter clothes protected him from the knife of Robert-Fran\u00b8cois Damiens. This ruler\u2019s finance minister Machault d\u2019Arnouville attempted to establish a 5 percent income tax that, unlike previous taxes, was imposed on everyone. This ruler, whose minister was Cardinal Fleury, had multiple mistresses, including Madame de Pompadour. For the point, name this French monarch who ruled during the Wars of Spanish and Austrian Succession in the 1700s after succeeding the Sun King.", "answer": "<b> Louis XV</b> [fifteenth] of France", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Chain Home system, part of the Dowding system, was one of the early users of this technology. The Pinetree Line was part of a project that used this technology during the Cold War. One use of this technology was shrouded in secrecy, with carrots instead praised during the Battle of Britain for helping the early detection of Luftwaffe fighters at night. For the point, name this technology that uses long electromagnetic waves, whose Doppler variety is used in meteorology.", "answer": "<b> RADAR</b> (or<b> radio detection and ranging</b>, prompt on \u201cradio\u201d)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s history is the subject of the Ibadan School, established by Kenneth Dike. One leader of this country, Yakubu Gowon, gave a speech proclaiming \u201cno victim, no vanquished\u201d at the end of its civil war. That civil war in this country led Bernard Kouchner and others to establish Doctors Without Borders. The Igbo people attempted to break away from this country and establish the Republic of Biafra. For the point, name this most populous African country whose capital moved from Lagos to Abuja in 1991.", "answer": "<b> Nigeria</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This composer\u2019s final work was prefaced with a quatrain and depicts a wood spirit. In one piece, this composer uses the English horn to depict a bird that guards the land of the dead. A piece by this man, originally written for the Press Celebrations, was performed under alternate names to prevent Russian censorship. This man was inspired by Elias Lonnrot\u2019s<em> Kalevala</em> to write tone poems such as<em> Tapiola</em> and <em>The Swan of Tuonela</em>. For the point, name this composer of<em> Finlandia</em>.", "answer": "Jean<b> Sibelius</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "For the point, name this Virginian colonial uprising.", "answer": "<b> Bacon</b>\u2019s Rebellion", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Submarines developed by this force include the<em> Hunley</em>, and the USS<em> Monitor</em> was built to counter the modified USS<em> Merrimack</em>, owned by this force, at the Battle of Hampton Roads. For the point, name this navy that fought against the Anaconda Plan during the U.S. Civil War.", "answer": "<b> Navy</b> of the<b> Confederacy</b> (accept<b> Confederate</b> States of America or<b> CSA</b> for \u201cConfederacy;\u201d do not accept references to the USA or America; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This author founded a journal whose literary editor was Jessie Faucet. This sociologist wrote a book whose opening chapter, \u201cOf Our Spiritual Strivings,\u201d states that the title group experiences America through \u201cthe veil\u201d and develops a \u201cdouble consciousness.\u201d This first editor of<em> The Crisis</em> advocated for the development of a small African-American elite, the \u201ctalented tenth,\u201d which was opposed to the Atlanta Compromise proposed by Booker T. Washington. For the point, name this sociologist who wrote<em> The</em> <em>Souls of Black Folk</em> and co-founded the NAACP.", "answer": "W. E. B.<b> DuBois</b> (William Edward Burghardt DuBois)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {"question": "The winning side in this battle took the losing side\u2019s mobile field brothels and sent the prostitutes to be \u201cre-educated.\u201d Operation Vulture rescued the forces of the losing side in this battle. Charles Piroth blew himself up with a grenade during this battle, which was preceded by Jean Gilles\u2019 [zhon zheel\u2019s] Operation Castor. The winning side in this battle was assisted by the anti-artillery provided by Vo Nguyen Giap. For the point, name this 1954 victory for Ho Chi Minh\u2019s Viet Minh that ended French occupation in modern-day Vietnam.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Dien Bien Phu</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One election win for this politician was aided by George Mahoney\u2019s slogan of \u201cYour home is your castle, protect it.\u201d This man\u2019s resignation led to the first application of Section 2 of the Twenty-Fifth Amendment. This first Greek-American governor of Maryland was the second to resign in his highest position after John C. Calhoun, after he pled no contest to charges of tax evasion in 1973. For the point, name this man replaced by Gerald Ford as Vice President of Richard Nixon.", "answer": "Spiro<b> Agnew</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One secretary of war from this party had an affair with Christine Keeler, resulting in the Profumo Affair. This party removed its country\u2019s currency from the European Exchange Rate Mechanism, resulting in Black Wednesday. Prime Ministers from this party have included Harold Macmillan and John Major. In May 2015, this party defeated Ed Miliband\u2019s party to retain control of the House of Commons. For the point, name this party which has led British Parliament since defeating Labour, with Liberal Democrat help, in 2010 under David Cameron.", "answer": "<b> Conservative</b> Party of the United Kingdom", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "One piece by this artist, which was ridiculed as a \u201csnowman in a bathrobe,\u201d depicts the author of <em>La pere Goriot</em>. Six men are depicted with bare feet and nooses around their neck in another of his works, which commemorates their sacrifice in a siege during the Hundred Years\u2019 War. This sculptor of<em> Balzac</em> and<em> The Burghers of Calais</em> also depicted a seated man with his right elbow on his left knee. For the point, name this French sculptor of<em> The Thinker</em>, part of his Dante-inspired<em> Gates of Hell</em>.", "answer": "Auguste<b> Rodin</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Arthur Waley, the first translator of this work into English, believed that it was finished, but other translators such as Edward Seidensticker disagree. This work\u2019s protagonist has a mid-life crisis after turning 40 and contemplates his future in the \u201cIllusion\u201d chapter, which precedes \u201cVanished into the Clouds,\u201d a completely blank chapter. The protagonist of this work marries Princess Aoi in its first chapter and has an affair with Lady Fujitsubo. For the point, name this Heian-era work by Lady Murasaki, often considered the world\u2019s first novel.", "answer": "<b> Tale of Genji</b> (or<b> Genji monogatari</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "David Wooster\u2019s occupying forces were deeply unpopular in an unsuccessful attempt of this action, in which Richard Montgomery died. Isaac Brock\u2019s victory at the Battle of Queenston Heights foiled another attempt to perform this action during the War of 1812, and Benedict Arnold was forced to retreat from Quebec during his effort to do this during the Revolutionary War. For the point, name this military action, often unsuccessfully taken by U.S. troops to capture a northern neighbor.", "answer": "U.S.<b> invasion</b>s of<b> Canada</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Francis I succeeded, for the point, what retired Pope?", "answer": "Pope Emeritus<b> Benedict XVI</b> (prompt on partial, accept Joseph Aloisius<b> Ratzinger</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "California\u2019s 2008 Proposition 1A allocated about 10 billion dollars to the funding of this technology. The Japanese Shinkansen and French TGV were early examples of this technology. Elon Musk\u2019s hyperloop is an alternative to developing one of these technologies in California, which is only currently present in the United States as Amtrak\u2019s Acela. For the point, name this technology that would allow for rapid intercity travel.", "answer": "<b> high speed rail</b>ways or<b> high speed train</b> or<b> bullet train</b> (prompt on \u201ctrain\u201d or \u201crailroads\u201dor \u201crailways\u201d)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "The planned \u201cCordoba House\u201d was one of these locations that led to protests against its developer, Sharif El-Gamel, in 2010. For the point, name these religious locations, such as the planned Park51 near Ground Zero, which usually contain niches pointed towards Mecca.", "answer": "<b> mosque</b>s (prompt on \u201chouses of worship\u201d)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s contributions to the 1964 World\u2019s Fair included his development of \u201cAudio-Animatronics.\u201d<em>Great Moments with Mr.</em> <em>Lincoln</em> and<em> The Hall of Presidents</em> were created by this man, whose\u201cExperimental Prototype Community of Tomorrow\u201d was turned into an amusement park, featuring the\u201cWorld Showcase\u201d in 1982. For the point, name this founder and namesake of amusement parks in Anaheim and Orlando, the latter of which includes EPCOT and the Magic Kingdom.", "answer": "Walt<b> Disney</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "One pope with this name denounced Holy Roman Emperor Frederick II during the Council of Lyon. One pope with this name denounced the Peace of Westphalia in the bull<em> Zelo Domus</em> <em>Dei</em> and is the subject of Francis Bacon\u2019s<em> Screaming Popes</em> series of paintings, based on works of Diego Velazquez. Another pope with this name convoked the Fourth Lateran Council and called for the Albigensian Crusade. King John was excommunicated by a pope with, for the point, what common name, meant to invoke a lack of guilt?", "answer": "<b> Innocent</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}